Your source for Orthodox books, podcasts, videos, and more.
We are ancient faith ministries.
He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall, and
he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him.
And they will pray.
and bless and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits, 1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4 through 5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels, demons,
and saints. In our time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism,
to see and to know reality as it truly is. What is this spiritual reality like? How do we engage with
with it well. How do we purr me?
every day life with spiritual presence.
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick,
and Father Stephen DeYoung host this live Colin show,
focused on enchantment in creation,
the union of the scene and unseen as made by God
and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Good evening, giant killers, dragon slayers,
succubus slaughterers, footstompers of dragon-footed giants.
You're the Saint Florida Spirit.
podcast and my co-host, the very Reverend Dr. Father Stephen Diyang is with me
straight from the swamp in Lafayette Louisiana. And I'm Father and her
Steve Adamick in Emmaus, Pennsylvania, atop the Eldritch Tower of
podcasting perched above a gateway to the underworld. And we are live. And if
you are listening to us live, you can call us at 855-237-2346. And you
can talk to us. And we're going to get to your calls in the second half of
the show. And Mats Kachoo, the tank Richter will be taking your calls.
sitting with
here in the studio right now. Is Dr. Christopher Phillips, professor of meteorology at Valparaiso
University, who besides studying how to protect our planet from meteors thrown at us through
space, as almost happened to the planet Duran 5 and season 3 episode 8 of Star Trek The
Original Series for the world's hollow and I've touched the sky. Apparently also
heard about the Orthodox Church.
Kurok was happy.
Apparently you also learned about the Orthodox Church through this great podcast and then went cre-
and joined it. So hello Dr. Phillips. Thank you for all you do to protect the Earth from meteors and your screwdriver.
Thank you.
This episode is sponsored by the Orthodox Studies Institute at St. Constantine College, which exists to advance the study and application of Orthodox Christianity in faithfulness to Holy Tradition.
OECI's next live course is Tolkien, God's Monsters, and Myth taught by none other than your humble servant.
The class starts on November 12th, runs for five weeks.
to check out the syllabus and the sign up go to orthodoxstudies.org slash LOS. So tonight is our
annual Halloween episode. So of course we're going to discuss the darker side of the spiritual world,
namely demons and how they were understood in the ancient world, including even as late as the
fourth century. And we should mention even after even after even after we should miss. Oh,
Yeah, I didn't think anything happened after the fourth century that you were remotely interested in.
Not so much, but you know, we got some, we got some Santa Gusta knocking around this episode.
There we go, there we go. So but yes, we should say that this is, we're going to have to drop a little parental advisory here at the beginning of this episode.
There are some, some sections, especially in the third half, but throughout really, that parents may want to listen to before they share it with younger children.
Demon sales.
That's why we'll be discussion of demons sex.
Yes, before before the episode started, John Maddox had something about sorted
details. And I'm like, well, if you're in disordered details, have we got a show for you tonight?
Who this might be the one that finally gets father Steven canceled. So who knows we should
tune in. This could be the last episode. Every time you're like, shut it off, turn it
all dude so to fall the trash compactors and the detention level that'll be
the one. So yes, what are demons? Where did demons come from anyway? Are they born in little
little demon villages? Yes. No, that's not true. Are you thinking of the smurfs? Who? Oh, I know
in the 80s they told you those were demons. I mean, they did come from an evil wizard.
That's a weird experiment. Well, the evil wizard was the bad guy though. Yeah. Wait, did he make,
I think he just made smurfette.
I didn't see Bates' roof.
see my smurf floor is not really that great.
See, there are certain parallels here, right?
It's kind of a reverse nephilim, right?
Like he creates the only female smurf.
Oh, just to do the other smurfs.
What a great lead in to the real.
So, smurf vet is a watcher?
I don't know, we could go with it.
I'm gonna go with that.
Smurf vet's a watcher, everybody.
I mean, the cat's day was as real, so I mean, there's something.
the guy me in there. Yes.
We're a lot of the nose smurf at left her former estate
So yeah, where do you smurf's argument?
End demons would have been a good one for a state. Yeah
Yeah, yeah, yeah
Gargamel should have focused more on curing his male pattern baldness and less on
Trying to I think was he trying to eat them or something weird?
I I think that's true. I
Man, again my smurf floor is lacking.
It's been a long time since I delved into that.
It's your anti-scan Danavian racism.
I like Scandinavians.
They have excellent pastries among other things.
That's a stereotype.
Anyway.
So yeah, demons, demons.
What are they good for?
I'm from absolutely nothing.
But, um,
uh, so we're starting with
Where did say the Greeks and the Romans think they came from?
Yeah.
And so we're starting as is your want more than mine with some etymology.
I know.
I still don't have the jingle like lined up here, even though I said earlier today I would
do it.
So I could sing it for everybody.
See, it's the lack of follow through, Father Ed.
I know.
Father of Andrews et tamale
G-Conner. There we go. Like just last night Bible study, I was talking about the sacrificial offerings you would have to make for having not completed your vow.
Oh, are you in are you in Leviticus?
Yeah.
Or, oh, nice, nice.
But anyway, yeah.
So Greek, of course, is where we get the word demon from.
Yeah.
Daemon, Daemon.
Daemon, Daemon, which not a great Greek.
cranky. Yeah.
That's true.
Yeah.
And not just a computer program that manages things in the background.
Yes.
What's just kind of creepy when you think about it.
The handle by a demon.
I know.
Oh, that's not true.
Yeah.
So, yeah, Damon, they want demon comes from a proto-indulter European route.
That means dividers, like in your desk, dividers and no.
Yeah.
Dividing up, right?
Sharing out, apportioning.
Yeah land land thing. Yeah, and I mean this this comes from this idea as we've talked before about these territorial
Spirits right spirits that over our over a thing or you know, yeah, please also very very early on takes on the connotation
Also, I'm having to do with fate and destiny
Yeah
Because of course you got to remember paganism
some incredibly
deterministic, right, completely fatalist. So then in Latin, we're talking about the word
genius, the modern use of which term is analogical to its original usage. And that actually is a word,
comes from Gainey, which was...
a word that meant a father, specifically a father in the sense of a producer of offspring.
Like someone who fathers.
Yeah, so like generate Genesis, that kind of stuff is all.
Genus.
And Gintus, which is where the word Gentiles comes from.
Gentes is Gentes' niche in basically in
in Latin sort of like patrimony right it's connected to the idea of having a
single father or being a father to offspring the people of a nation being the
children of the nation right but was of course seen in spiritual terms right and
we'll get into that more in a little bit we're gonna start though with our
our Greek friends.
our pagan Greek friends from long ago and far away. And that begins with Hesseat.
Kettle Hesseat. As I commented to you earlier today, Hesseat is a pain to read
because it's basically in the same Greek as Homer. But when you learn Homeric Greek,
you learn Homer's vocabulary, which means...
18 different words for like spear and shield. Right.
Yes, you just learn all these like words having to do with war and weaponry and fight.
Yeah, I mean by the time yeah by the time you're done reading, you know, the Iliad, right?
You know all the different ways to describe stabbing someone in the neck with a spear.
Yeah, so then you read Hessey and he's talking about like muses and waters and glades and nymphs and things and you don't know what's going on.
Right. Because you didn't learn any of that vocabulary.
Um.
I see it is also even more poetic and in some cases there are lacune and his works,
chunks missing.
This is all just me venting past frustrations in Greek language study, basically at this
point.
Not everything is preserved like a cuneiform tablet.
Yeah, so yeah, see fired, you can throw those things on the ground, it'll dent the floor.
That's what I'm talking about.
But Hesiod, for those who aren't super familiar with Hesiod, Hesiod, we're talking about,
I mean there's no firm date. We're talking about the beginning of the first millennium BC.
So we're talking roughly, usually people peg Homer around 800. Hesiod is probably a little
earlier. And what Hesseyet is doing is mostly...
compiling oral tradition, particularly related to Greek religion. Now that Greek
religion is all mixed up with historical traditions, but historical traditions
not like Homer's historical traditions, but historical traditions as in the
beliefs of the Greek people at the time about their origins.
Yeah, as a
people. Yeah, this is what they thought their story was about. Yeah. And so sort of their self-understanding
and of their identity. And so the the work that everybody reads is called the Theogony, which is
basically the generation of the gods. It's about the different gods coming into being. Yeah, if you're
you're looking to read a primary source about sort of the basis for Greek mythology.
this is the one you go to. Right. This is where you start at least. Yeah. This is where you get the
two rounds of the succession myth. First urinosa and gaya and then cronus and rea and then
finally Zeus. Zeus and Hera. Yeah. You get that and that's as we've talked about on the show
before he's incorporating there. Both like an early Indo-European religious layer.
instead of traditions with a semitic version of the succession myth, it's probably coming from
Phoenicia and sort of blending those together. He's bringing all of these traditions into one
place and blending them together. And so one of the he has other works however that we have including
hymns and all kinds of things are lumped in. Of course, we're not sure.
all those hymns were actually written by this one guy named Hessey it. Yeah. Yeah. They're
just, they date from that era. And so I mean, even, even the stuff that has Homer's name
on it, there's a whole big world of people to say, whoa, who's Omar anyway? Right. Because
of course, we don't have copies anywhere near the original. We don't have no, no, no,
You know, so you can't prove it.
But that's just, that's ancient history.
Right.
I mean, you can't.
prove right that's how it is anything that's why when you hear one of these modernists going around saying, oh, can you prove that that happened in ancient history?
The answer is no, you can't prove anything happened in ancient history, right? Just right. Like prove Alexander the Great existed. You can't. Right. Like.
That's.
So, but one theme and for our purposes here, the theme we want to draw out of
is that he talks about the origin of Daemonus, right, of demons. And for him, it's... he makes
abundantly clear that, I mean, assuming that there's a hymn there, just a single hymn. These
works make abundantly clear that in these traditions, the Daemonus used to be people and used to be
in particular heroes. Now, heroes...
is kind of a technical term in Greek. Right? We talk about heroes just,
hey, somebody did something cool, right? Like, yeah. Now, there's some money in the bucket with the
bell ringer at Christmas. You're a hero, right? No, it's kind of like a species. Right. Right.
Because the heroes of myth, they did do these great exploits. That's where our use of the word
here, O comes from.
Right.
So we use it sort of analogically to refer to exploits.
That's why-
we had to talk about superheroes, right?
Like Superman is a superhero,
because he does all these exploits, right?
And say, Hercules did all these exploits, right?
But that wasn't the core of what being a hero was.
Usually you were part divine and part human.
So these were quasi-divine, quasi-human beings.
Who accomplished these feats?
and who when they...
died then became sort of their spirit lived on and became a day-mone that was
evolved at various spiritual activity. So in the theogin, in theogin E997,
E997 is the line number by the way, not a page number. Most early Greek texts,
when you quote them with numbers, there's not like a single edition where there
are page numbers. Right, you list the line numbers. Yeah.
And the
The line numbers are kind of arbitrary too.
They're from a particular collection of classics.
But suffice to say that's how it's listed.
So this is line number 997.
He talks about in the Theogony, Fetan becoming, who was one of the heroes, becoming a
day-moan.
But then in works and days, which is a lesser-read, as theotic work, in lines 122 to 126,
He talks about how Zeus.
transforms heroes and by them being transformed into Daymone at the time of their death, they sort of become his children if they weren't already now some of them already were because
you know, do you see on the loose.
Yeah dude got around but you know if they weren't directly they sort of became them by virtue of
of becoming becoming Daymones worst god ever.
Nuh.
So yeah, yeah Zeus too, man
so
You have this picture then of the sort of great man
Right who are considered divine at least partially they die
Their spirits then become spirits in the world so
One thing a lot of people don't know I know we've mentioned it on the show before
I don't know how much step we've got into on it. Is that...
Greek temples. And this is, you know, this is the level of nerd I am. I was playing Assassin's
Creed Odyssey and got all excited that their temples were actually correct. Oh. There's
a lot of other stuff that's historically iffy, like the female protagonist, but they got
the temples right? That you have the main body.
of the temple, which is the temple to a god. Yeah. And then adjoining it, there is a shrine to a hero.
Yeah. Yeah. So if you're talking about like Athens or any other city, you're going to have the
main temple to the god, right, the big temple, and there's going to be a shrine to the founder,
right? The here was the founder of the city, right?
It was probably considered a child of the city's God.
right before and or after their death and becoming a day mon. And they generally considered
that the grave, and I obviously just no way to prove this, right, and excavations,
but I mean how would you even demonstrate this anyway? Whether there was even a grave in a lot
of these we don't know, but supposedly that shrine was the site of the grave of the person,
Right, till they left their body to...
become a daybone and their body was buried there. But those shrines were seen to localize
that daybone in a way not identical to but parallel to the way in which the temple would
localize the god.
Yeah, it's sort of anchors them there.
Right. Because we've talked a lot about, when we talked about idolatry and stuff, how
You localize a God in a temple in an idol to try to...
be able to interface with it. And often that means manipulate it leverage it get it to do what you want right yeah
Whereas
With one of these day monists sort of these wandering
Spirits that was the problem the problem was now they're just out there wandering around and
So you would build the shrine to localize them in order to sort of give them a home
home.
All right, yeah.
Because if they're left wandering, they're going to be
kind of unhappy and cranky and might do terrible things to your city.
Right.
They'd be angry and mean because they have no place and no one's honoring them and
no one's doing anything for them.
Which, I mean, this fits in with the general Greek idea that people need to be
buried in order for their spirits to be at rest.
Right.
You know, for non-heroes, non-day ones, they have to be buried so that they can
enter the enter into Hades.
Otherwise they're kind of left hanging.
Yeah.
Yeah, so this is you put a bit of places shrine and then you come to the shrine and you make offerings
Right, yeah, we're out the
Sacrifice or out the blood of sacrifices into the grave
And you offer incense
Right to the hero right as well to sort of keep them happy and pacify but
This extended to by the way to ruined cities
So Greeks avoided ruin.
cities. Yeah, hungry culture. You stayed away from ruined cities because the the day
mones that even some of the gods of that city were sort of wandering the ruins. Yeah. And
not being worshiped. So and we're unhappy because of that. Yeah. Right. And so that was
the stuff of horror movies for Greeks. They would not like if they're on a log trip and
they need a shelter for the night, they would not be going into an abandoned city. Right.
would be like the weird
saw Shaq in Texas, right? Like you don't go in there, whatever you do, right? So we also get,
right? So that's sort of the connection to heroes. Of course, we've also read, and we're not
going to read it again because we've read it several times in several episodes. The quotes from
Plato about the age of cronus, sort of the golden age in the path.
in which the day-mones were given, the monists were given by lot, were given the different
nations to shepherd.
And this develops, right, we talked about that connected to the Tower of Babel story in
Genesis, but also in later traditions, it's not just nation.
but people, right, that people have them. And Socrates, of course, is exhibit A. We've
read those quotes too. Socrates talking about Desmonion. It's sort of unclear, and this is by
lot too like there are a lot of people right people different people are given to
these different demons
It's not clear if it's everyone or just particular people.
And part of the reason it's not clear
is we have to remember, and this is gonna be important
to remember when we're talking about the Romans here
in a minute too, that ancient people,
like ancient Greeks and ancient Romans,
didn't consider all humans to be people.
Yeah, you're right.
Not all people are persons.
Yeah, so like I know you've been in the same place
been told, especially about a lot of our Greek friends about the wonders of Athenian democracy,
but the Athenian demos was pretty tightly constricted in terms of who can vote.
Yeah, right.
Like the demos wasn't like every human who lived in Athens.
Or even every man.
You know, like it wasn't even every man.
It wasn't even every free man.
Right.
It wasn't even every native born free man.
I mean it was literally an error
aristocracy. Yeah, so because of those aristocratic ideas, you'll get general statements, right,
about like, oh, well, everyone has one. But then you have to investigate what they mean
by everyone. Yeah, everyone who's everyone. Sort of like the American Declaration of Independence
saying all men are created equal. And it's like, well, except if you don't own land or
your slave or your dot.
literally a man you're a woman right? So you have to, you know, all men doesn't necessarily mean all men.
Yeah. And I mean, and Rome, you know, we're going to talk about Romans, but Romans were,
weren't, weren't any better at this by the way. Literally, they're worse. They're worse way worse.
I mean, they literally had the category of non-persona for most people in the Roman Empire.
Yeah. Yeah.
So...
But they were associated with people, right? And Socrates, of course, had this, this
Desmonion who would whisper wisdom to his soul and give him guidance, stop him from doing
things, sometimes, or cause him to do things, as he says, very creepily. But it's important
here. So the idea of demonic possession, this is where that originates. So I know we hear
demonic possession and especially this time of year you think of like
the exorcist, right? Or since we just read the Gospel last weekend about the origins of Devil'd
Ham, you think of like Legion and the pigs, right? And that kind of thing. But that's not where the
term starts being used. The term starts being used in Greek with the idea that this person possesses
a day-mone. There's a day-mone who possesses him. Yeah, and that was seen as a positive thing.
Yeah, Socrates possesses...
one, one possessed Socrates, they were linked their whole life. So this is, if this is, if this is
sounding like a weird inversion to you, you're thinking the right way. This is sort of a guardian demon.
Yeah. This is a guardian devil. And in Greek religion,
Oh, my name is not coming to me.
When it comes to me, I'll come back to it.
But in Greek religion, demonus occupy this realm between gods and humans.
And so the, they're neither the same as the high
God's at least. There's sort of a fuzzy border. Yeah, there is a muse, a demon, or a God. Right,
right. Right. Right. There's sort of a fuzzy border there. Right. And especially with the ones
that you know, used to be human or used to be demi-humans, you can kind of see. Yeah. Yeah. So
there's kind of a fuzzy border there. It's hard to do like strict categorization. And the way
the term gets used.
gets used fuzzily at the border, right?
I can even show you texts that refer to Zeus as a daymone.
Yeah.
So, you know, this isn't a lot of times
we talk about these things on the show.
And we get feedback that people are confused.
And the reason they're confused
is that they're trying to do these like hard
and fast categories, right?
like these b a
beings are in this gods of the nation's category. And these other beings are in this demoness
category. And, right? And not everything in life works that way.
No, I mean, I mean, like just think of the word spirit, right? You could, you know, the
human spirit, spirit of a nation, the holy spirit, like these are all we use the word
spirit for them, but these are radically different kinds of beings. Right. And since...
the ancient Greek pagans were talking about were not scholastic philosophers or theologians.
They didn't tax-automize and classify everything. They just didn't. They didn't nail things down
like that. Hensiate is mostly poetry, right? Not prose. Yeah, in fact, the idea that someone would
would do science without poetry was just not a thing in much of human history.
Yeah.
So this is something we talked about very early on, right?
We can't plug everything into a spreadsheet.
Right, you take a poem, you take a poem that's in a word document,
you try and imported it into a spreadsheet,
you're gonna get weird results, man.
So we have to just let some things be a little hazy,
a little evocative, and not try and nail them down.
Because if you try and nail them down,
you'll end up confusing yourself.
But so they're in general, they're in this realm between gods and men.
And what that concretely means is that they are primarily energetic beings.
And I energetic, I don't mean like, they have a lot of pep and vigor.
They're well-foculated.
No, it's, yeah, it's this sense of, so energies in the theological and philosophical sense
is working, working,
in is what it literally means, but yeah, it's that sense of acting upon, you know, yeah,
they're countering inaction.
Yeah, action.
They're countered inaction, meaning for the most part, there are exceptions, right?
But for the most part, you don't have people like seeing and talking to and interacting
with the models.
Right? Yeah.
The Greek gods will appear to people, seduce people,
fornicate with people, if you're Zeus, right?
Some of the others, right?
We'll do all those kind of things.
Daymonis primarily don't.
Yeah, they sort of come upon you.
They're experienced.
Feel them. Yeah.
Yeah.
Their influence is felt.
Right? They act upon people.
They're encountered in a more sort of existential way.
Yeah. I like like like a young couple
go around the woods.
and then they are filled with lust for each other,
they would say that a demon had come upon them,
like that was the sense.
There was a day, the day-mone of the woods had, yeah.
And because of this,
they're very rarely depicted in Greek iconography.
So you'll have all kinds of depictions of Zeus
in various forms and other gods and goddesses
and divine beings.
You rarely have depictions of demoness
after the
death, right? I've heard you lose while he was alive, right? Or the founder while he was alive,
doing one of his great feats, like depicting this story from his life, but not afterward.
Yeah. Right. They're not depicted. The biggest, biggest exception to that is Eros.
Yes, the Sun, for Dany. Yeah, Eros you do find depictions of less commonly than you think.
Depictions of Eros are actually more common in Renaissance art than they are in
Pay.
Greek art. Yeah, somewhat amazingly. She probably just mentioned at least just for the, you know,
sake of clarity that Aphrodite is not the goddess of love. She's the goddess of seduction. So,
but there's some, there's some griff, some griff, grist for the mill, not grift.
It's probably some grift going on there, too. Yeah, well, you know, if Pashot was listening,
Right. Hero. Way more common in Renaissance art.
Then in pagan Greek art
Though there are other very graphic things in pagan Greek art that you haven't seen because
Yes, don't don't just Google stuff up especially with your kids next to you. Yes, but some of this really it's tough
I won't say what this happens with something earlier today when we were preparing for this show and father Andrew Google something
I mentioned I have regrets. Yes
A few I'm scarred for life
made me want to become a
But Eros is, for example, referred to in this symposium as the Great Daemon, and associated
with shockingly Dionysus.
Yes.
Who could figure?
So that gives you a little bit of a picture.
of what's going on with the Greeks in terms of Daemonus.
Now let's talk about the Romans.
And so now we're going to be talking about Genii,
which is the plural of genius.
Not to be confused with Genii's or Genii.
Yeah.
Although I have a suspicion there's some relation.
But there may be, yeah, maybe.
That's a rabbit hole we're not going down right now.
Yeah.
So a genius was a spirit for the Roman religion that was associated with a person, with a place,
with a geographical feature or with a people group.
Yeah.
And they would say that like every person has it, but remember, not everyone is a person.
Not everyone is a person.
Yeah.
Right.
also though.
striking a blow for women's rights. They believed women were possessed by demons too.
There were, so brief note on that, right? You may be thinking, well, there were women like
the Pythian oracle and the oracle at Delphi, right? Who were women who were possessed. They
They were female slaves.
I'm asked by demons.
Right.
Like, if you read, like just read, for instance, the aned, you know, when the civil gets possessed
by Apollo, yeah, it's not like a nice experience.
Yeah.
So there's a big difference between that and what Socrates said was going on with his
day mode.
Right.
He has more of a relationship.
As the Romans more broadly had junior related to
you know, that were spirits associated with women, when we're talking about a genius associated
with a person. And then places, right, these are, this is similar to Greek religion, this
cigarette places, groves, springs of water, right, etc., etc. Geographical features means
like a mountain of valley.
cave, right, as opposed to just a place in general, right? So you might have a mountain
that has some genius, some spirit associated with the whole mountain, but then there may
be individual shrines, glades, things on the mountain associated with other spirits.
Yeah. Right. And that was particular places on the mountain.
Yeah, and also like people groups. So for instance, like with Rome, the genius of Rome is...
the Roma patria, you know, like the goddess Rome, basically. And Athens, I mean, by the way,
the name of Athens and Greek, everybody is Athena, like it's literally Athena. It's
exactly the same as the goddess. So, you know, that's, that's who their genius would be
from the Romans point of view.
For the Romans way of view, right. And this, of course, since we're picking on the Renaissance
and enlightenment as we were.
Yeah, we don't remember them anywhere near as much as we do 19th century go look at early American
I'm talking about like early 19th century and early French Republic
Iconography
right
Lady Liberty was supposed to be the genius of America. Oh, yeah
Yeah, and and what is you know like the apotheosis of Washington that's in the the capital dome
I mean is that is that Washington becoming a daymon?
just put it out there. That is what that is. What was the other name for Lady Liberty? What was her name?
The female figure. Oh, they used it the depictions of manifest destiny. And
trying to look this up now. This was the Holy Spirit. Yeah.
Yeah.
I mean there is this idea of the goddess.
Libertas. Yeah, no, no, no, she had a particular name. Was it Columbia?
Oh, I mean, yeah, I think Columbia actually was this idea of
yeah, goddess of America kind of that's what the District of Columbia is named after. Yeah,
yeah, yeah. Yeah. So yeah, lots of paganism in early 19th century history.
We've talked.
about that before, how the rise of nationalism always brings about a kind of return to paganism.
Including today, where I saw a person promoting Aristotle's view of natural slavery
in the present day.
Yeah.
Yeah. So I've seen that actually here and there. Decide that certain groups of people are
fit to be slaves. Yeah, this is how you bick with as paganism is when Christianity starts to
recede, it comes Russian right back in. Yeah, it's not going to be any better this time. So
pick your poison atheists. So there is, so we said there's a genius associated with a person
with a place.
with a geographical feature with a people group, right?
And the connection between the spirit,
this spirit, and the person place thing, right, what have you,
is sort of this direct reciprocal relationship,
meaning they share traits and features.
Yeah, so like if you're if you're genius is
let's say warlike in his personality, then the person or
nation that's attached to may well be warlike as well.
Like, he's sort of similar personalities.
Not super clear like which direction the influence goes always.
Although it seems to be pretty clear with a person that the
influence is the spirit influencing the person.
But remember it comes up.
unclear is like a volcano. Right. Is it that, you know, a volcano burst out? And so therefore
a genius was attracted to it and was influenced by it or that the genius is doing that to the earth.
Yeah. Yeah. Not completely clear. But in any case, despite this close and reciprocal
relationship, they were also distinguishable. Right. Meaning they weren't the same being.
right so we're talking about this
more in a minute, but the daymoan that possessed a person was not just their spirit, right,
like their spirit.
Yeah, no, it's a separate entity.
It is a separate entity, but that is allotted to a person in a sense is obviously more powerful
than a person.
Yeah.
Sort of guiding and shepherding that person.
So again, we have this idea of guardian demon.
For the record, the Adosius when he became emperor at the end of the four century,
outlawed sacrificial offerings to genii.
Because people would offer them to their own.
And I mean, that's a heck of a thing to do for the Roman emperor because, for centuries,
the test of patriotism was offering sacrifice to the genius of the emperor.
Yes, this is just
you know, having to make all these offerings so that your genius doesn't become mad and kill you
or to keep it at bay or to get it to stop driving you to crimes. Just one of the many beautiful
pagan traditions that theodosis outlawed that intolerant jerk. Yeah. So we have to touch on, as I
briefly mentioned, a certain revisionist interpretation of this that has arisen more recently.
And this is based on man, we're just bashing the Enlightenment today.
We've talked about this before that contemporary scholarship, and this is really a recent thing.
This is like a 20th century thing.
It started in the Enlightenment, but has really gained traction now.
In the Enlightenment, they sort of wanted to cast the Greek philosophers in particular
and also Roman philosophers as being very much
like them. So because say the French philosophes had decided that, oh, Roman Catholicism is
base superstition that the rabble believe, right? We're above it. They projected it into the past.
Oh, Plato, Aristotle, Socrates, they can't possibly have believed in all this pagan.
Right. Because we love those guys. That's even worse than that's even worse than Roman Catholicism.
right? So they can't possibly have believed that. They must have been above it.
And like I said, that's just a just intensified until now like you've got people trying to argue that
Hagle wasn't a Lutheran. He's like the most Lutheran guy in the world. If you read what he writes, like,
like Luther would have looked at him and been like, dang, right? Like,
you know, but somehow we got to read him in this way that he wasn't really religious because how could
He was smart.
Yes.
Which is.
just a stupid and weird bias. Okay. But the way that works itself out in this discussion
is they're like, well, wait, it's not critis can't possibly have believed in demons.
Right. Socrates is too smart. He can't have believed there was some spirit with sprignaut
soul. He can't believe that he must have just been talking about his own spirit, his own
soul. Right. That must be what he was talking about. That must be what all these philosophers
believed in because they couldn't believe that pay.
nonsense, of course. And so here's the kernel, right? The kernel of truth of that is that
when you get into the late third and early fourth centuries, especially in the fourth century, where we're talking about the last generation of pagans, right, of Greek and Roman pagans.
within the Roman Empire. Paganism changed a lot over the course of that last 85 to 100 years.
We talked about the
about that in some recent episodes, like with platyneus trying to sort of redo
platenism and make it more christianish, right? But the same happened to paganism.
They pretty much stopped sacrificing animals. For example, it was mostly incense
and prayers and hymns and stuff. What does that sound like?
So they were shifting or the influence of Christianity to try to...
survive, paganism became a very different thing. So when you look at some of those last generation
pagan philosophers like Labanius and stuff, they may have very much interpreted those earlier
texts that way because they were trying to find a more refined version of philosophy and paganism,
right? That would get around Christian critiques, yeah, right? Of their beliefs. But it's very clear.
It is abundantly clear. It is inc-
reveredably clear. That's Socrates, Plato, Aristotle, fully believed in
in Daemonus, fully believed in spirits, believed in the spiritual world, believed
it literally, Aristotle's Academy was, or his school was inside a temple to
Apollo. These were full-blooded pagans, right? I'll be it
of a very intellectual sort, you know, who intellectualized elements of their practice
and that kind of thing, but we're very religious in their time and place.
So if anybody comes to you with that interpretation, just know they're trying to retcon it because
they're embarrassed by religion.
That's what they're making that argument.
But so as we mentioned, right, to sort of sum up what we've been talking about in this
first half.
Right, there was very much...
I'm on Greek and Roman pagans, this belief in people having a guardian devil, having a guardian demon,
a genius that was associated with them, with whom they interacted over the course of their life.
Yeah, and for pagans, that was a positive good thing. I mean, you had like a little god on your side.
Right. Or at least who you could placate and mullify when not. And so,
So...
the the exorcisms that we do in the Orthodox Church,
and which have always been done at Christian baptisms,
the exorcisms at the beginning were not just an O-just in case.
Yeah, it wasn't like, oh, oh, you know, maybe there's
some kind of demonic influence. Let's do this. No, no,
it was a sense of, hey, there's a lot of demons running around.
Well
And the pagans who were coming there had some demon yoke to their life, right in their own understanding, right?
Right. Right.
And that was being exercised at one of the places where we see the tradition regarding guardian angels,
which is in the Bible. For example, Christ talks about the little ones whose angels in heaven are
always before the father.
But one of the places where that's most clearly articulated is actually in the baptismal services.
Yeah, because you get at the beginning the exorcisms to drive them out, but then also a very specific
prayer that a guardian angel will be assigned to this person. Right. So here's a replacement,
like the replacement we've talked about with saints, right, and the gods of the nations,
but on a personal level.
Yep, right? On a personal level. The demon that's been influencing your life is now replaced,
right, with an angel who's going to guide you better and a better place. But you could also see
here the origin then of the things like the prayer to the guardian angel, right? But that is a very
different character than making blood offerings so that your demon won't kill you because it's mad,
No.
Yeah.
And that's not an exaggeration. That is literally had to do sometimes.
Literally a thing. Right. The prayer of the guardian angel has a very different character.
Right. Indeed. So yeah, so that that kind of replacement was something that happened on a personal level.
So yeah, so in next half we're going to talk about, we talked about now,
the Greeks of the Romans.
We're going to talk about this from maybe a second type of Jewish perspective.
But it's all right on this show.
All right.
We're going to take our first break and we'll be back soon and we're going to take a couple
calls and see you soon.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your
calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
855 AF
The centuries after the Protestant Reformation brought about a radical reinterpretation of
the epistles of Saint Paul, disconnected from any historical reality.
But Paul operated during his entire life as a faithful Pharisee within the Roman Jewish
world.
In Saint Paul the Pharisee, Jewish Apostle to all nations, Father Stephen D. Young
surveys Paul's life and writings, interpreting them within the
Holy Tradition of the Orthodox Church.
This survey is followed by DeYoung's interpretive translation of St. Paul's Epistles, which
deliberately avoids overly familiar terminology.
By using words and ideas grounded in 1st century Judaism, DeYoung hopes to unsettle commonly
held notions and help the reader reassess St. Paul in his historical context.
available now at store.AncientFace.com.
Again, that is store.AncientFace.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Welcome back everybody.
That's easy.
This is really too short.
This season, it is 855-AFRADIO!
That's right.
Wait!
Ooh!
I'm surprised you didn't use the word spooktacular, Father Steven.
So I don't know how many people remember this, but my childhood was haunted by a recurring
commercial for a one nine hundred number.
I remember all of you.
Here's spooky stories.
Oh, but the commercial had this jack-a-lantern and it was like heavy rotate because they're
trying to get kids to call and run up their parents' phone bills, right?
Rotations during say your thunder cat.
and your silver hawks, right?
And there's this horrible jack-o-lantern puppet.
Like, I mean, really poor production values.
I never imagined that.
For the amount of money they must have been making on this thing.
And it always started out, boo!
Did I scare you?
If you really want to be frightened,
oh, 1900, whatever the number was.
I, that does sound familiar.
Did I just trigger a flashback?
haha
Wow. Man, 100, 100 number is let alone six. I know. Man. All right. We are going to take
a couple of calls before we roll on into the second half. So first we have Julius and his
phone says he's in North Carolina. So Julius, welcome, Laura Spears podcast. Hey, follow
Andrew how are you?
I'm not going to stop liver over here.
That's right.
Finally.
Oh, I am.
Well, yeah, that's okay.
Whoever you are.
Yeah.
And yes, I'm at your old parish in Raleigh.
Oh, everyone at All Saints says, yeah.
Everyone at All Saints?
That's a lot of people today.
Are you one of the like 900 Catechumans they have right now?
No, we were received the last of the All Saints.
Oh, okay.
We're doing it with the loom in.
a noob. But we do have a great cat
of Cuban class right now, so it's really wonderful.
Yeah, I mean, it's hovering around a hundred these days, I think, right?
Yeah. That's nuts.
So it's on your mind, do this.
Well, one thing you guys for helping me with my modernism brain,
that I didn't even realize I had.
But from last week, but it ties in with this week, too.
But so one thing I'm really started to realize after life.
week is that and you've been talking about it tonight is everybody in ancient
world agreed that divine revelation was a thing and that seems to be what
really clashes with our modern brain that we gather information and facts are
this neutral thing and if you get the right fact or if you get enough facts and
you're good at it you will discover the truth through your interpretation skills
but it seems like everybody in the ancient world
agreed that the truth was something that had to be revealed to you from outside.
I wouldn't generalize that much because like people do learn things
from being taught or from observation. No, but I think he's pointing to, I mean far
be it for me to defend Julius after the snub here but the...
I think he's pointing to the difference.
it's sort of the views of where ideas come from.
Yeah, yeah.
Right.
So we thought about ideas and concepts are built out of facts, right?
You collect facts that build the concepts and ideas, right?
As opposed to them coming in from outside, right?
Yeah.
Well, yeah.
And especially like I said, the idea today, yeah, that like people just reject the Vine
Revelation in general, that like if you tell somebody, you know, oh, well, you know,
How do you know it's true?
Well...
you know it was revealed to me by the Holy Spirit. They're you know if they don't believe in it they're
gonna roll their eyes pretty much. Yeah. Yeah.
Elite on the inside they might be polite on the outside.
I mean less likely in North Carolina than up here in Yankee land but yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Which I have to say I almost understand because then you get into the problem of discernment
because lots of people you know we're going around. Right. Yeah.
very experienced in history saying, hey, guess what a spirit told me?
Yeah, so...
So what's your question, Julius?
Well, so that is the problem is, you know,
I'm looking at the CS Lewis quote
about there being no neutral ground
that God and Satan fight over every inch.
And I think that's another problem
that I'm having with my modern brain
is we have all these things that we say,
well, that's not good or bad.
It's just how you use it.
Or, you know, I even looked over the cross,
far, far across the aisle to Roman Catholicism
or they'll have like a patron saying...
the internet or the patron saint of, you know, something that seems totally enane, you know,
small shipping break, forgets or going fishing or whatever, you know, that oh, it's not good or bad,
you know, but you can use it for good or bad. And we have this idea of neutrality built into
everything, especially in marketing, right? They always want to use terms. They're like, well,
but we don't want you to judge or condemn.
We just want you to say,
that this is a feeling the consumer has.
So you're getting the postmodernism
which you talked about last week.
Everyone just has a perspective.
It's not all relative.
It's not good or bad.
So there's this neutrality
that's just really built into the modern age.
But CSU is very affirmative
that we don't really have neutrality.
Everything's good or bad.
And there seems to be the prescription
of the, sorry, the description given to us
by scripture to me, you know,
going into this.
the two paths, the sheep and the goats, there's a lot of it's one way or
the other. So can you talk about the Orthodox perspective on what is neutrality?
Where does it exist in the world? Or is it an illusion? Do we even have neutrality?
I mean, so you're either being obedient to God or you're not. But I think that one
of things I think maybe not obvious as obvious to people is that
obedience to God is actually way broader
and more inclusive than disobedience.
And so for instance, someone might say,
well, you know, okay, I gotta take the trash out.
That's not good or evil.
That's just something that I have to do.
But putting things in order and making them beautiful
and cultivating them is literally job one
as given to Adam and Eve, right?
So care taking.
this world and doing the things that have to be done and putting them in order, these
are the works that God gave us to do. That is an act of obedience. That is an act of
faithfulness. There are some things, of course, that it's not that it's neutral in itself,
but it is how you interact with it. Classic example will be drinking. It says in
Scripture that God makes wine for the gladness of the heart of man, but he didn't make it.
for drunkenness.
You know, so I think part of the problem of course is that questions of good and evil
are about human participation. They're not about a taxonomy of items.
There's no knowledge that doesn't include some kind of participation.
Right? So, you know, the idea of like there is no spiritual neutrality.
Often we think of certain actions.
as being neutral, but that's because we don't understand how they're either cooperating with God or
or not. A lot of that's probably just ignorance. Like I said, taking out the trash is an act of
order and beauty. So do that everybody. And therefore it's an act of faithfulness to God.
You know, all those little things that we do to keep ourselves and our lives in order, these are
of faithfulness to God. Holiness, really. I mean, they are acts of holiness. We might not think of them as
religious, but that's not what the call is. It's not to do things that we classify in this list of
churchy stuff. It's to do all the things that are obedience to the way that God made us to be and the
things He calls us to do. Father Stephen, do you have anything you wanted to add subtract? I'm actually...
Well, it's important that we don't confuse ontology and ethics.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, right. Where things or even people are good or evil as opposed to what they do or what they're used for is good or evil.
Yeah, right. Those are those are separate categories. And the danger of confusing those two is you end up with narcissism, right? Where the material world is somehow evil.
Right.
I'll use the example of alcohol that you just gave, right?
Because alcohol could be used for evil and may even be prevalently used to evil ends,
that means alcohol is somehow evil in and of itself, and can be done away with, right?
That's the Gnostic slippage, right?
Dancing, right, might lead to something else and therefore it's evil, right?
That kind of...
of things. So, nuclear power, right, you can use to create nearly infinite amounts of
carbon-neutral energy, right? You can also use the same technology to massacre millions
of innocent people. That doesn't mean that...
Nuclear efficient technology is neutral precisely, right?
It means that good or evil isn't a category that applies to nuclear efficient technology.
It applies to the use to which nuclear efficient technology is put.
It's put to a good user. It's put to an evil use.
But in and of itself, it again, neutral implies that it could be good.
or evil in and of itself. Right? Even if you think of something that you would say, well,
that's evil in and of itself. Like, let's say pornography. Right?
Pornography is not really a thing. Pornography is a subset of photography or film or videos or
right? And film videos, photography.
all have very good uses to which they're put.
And then also very evil usages of which pornography is one.
Yep. Right. So, yeah, neutral, again, I think is wrong
because that still places it on the moral compass.
And I think the issue there's that it's a category mistake.
Right. That good and evil are ethical categories
categories that we use to describe action.
I hope that's hopeful Julius.
I was like real quick father Steven.
Yes, I would love to ask you.
Have you ever seen the episode of
Cuombo where William Schattner plays
a fictional version of himself?
Yes, of course, yeah, where he has
the like little tiny moustache.
Yes, yeah, yeah, yeah, and he kind
of plays us all of the handy tropes
about himself in the end.
handy tropes about in cell in the air.
Yes, yes, he does like deliberate self-parity. Yes. Yeah. Yeah. It's really good. Okay. Well, I'm glad you've seen it. I was just gonna make sure you were where it existed. That mustaches unforgettable.
All right. Thanks for calling you. It's okay. We're gonna take one more call before we move on and we have Nicholas, who's apparently calling from Thessaloniki. Nicholas, welcome to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
Hello, can you hear me?
Yes, we hear you. What time is it there?
It is 3 o'clock in the morning.
All right. I'm on my way to the Holy Mountain.
Oh, okay.
And you're out of the on.
That's you.
So what's on your mind, Nicholas?
I was curious about Guardian Angels.
I know earlier in the show and also in previous episodes.
You have briefly mentioned them,
but I want to understand them a little better.
Like for example like
what were they guarding?
And what I have in my mind is like trying to get a grasp
on their activity in our life is thinking back to Genesis.
And I'm curious if it is like a good or true archetypal type
to think of the cherubim that God appoints to protect
the Garden of Eden after Adam and Eve get kicked out
with the flining sword to make sure that they don't have
access to the tree of wisdom and the tree of life anymore. I'm curious if the
Guardian Angels have the same sort of activity or if this is like does this
work as like a type in terms of like archetypes to make that comparison?
Yeah I mean interestingly like that cherub that's placed with the flaming
sword I think the exact language is as it guards the way to the tree of life.
But really what what's happening what what what that means
is that the chair was actually guarding Adam and Eve from killing themselves, you know,
spiritually from being crystallized in evil, right, so they don't have access to immortality
is the idea. Yeah, I mean, I think, you know, like it's, it's tempting to want to taxonomize
angelic beings. And of course, there's, there's some precedent for that, of course, you know,
like the ranks of angels and so forth.
But yeah, I think the function that you're talking about, the guarding, the guiding, you
know, the taking care of, right?
That is what a guardian angel does.
And that's what we, in our prayers to them that exist in our tradition, that's what we
ask them to do.
We ask them to help us be kept from sin, you know, to protect us from temptation, to
guard us from demonic attack, all that kind of stuff.
So yeah, that kind of guarding function that you see, not just with the angel at the door
of paradise, but many cases like, you know, the Archangel Raphael functions as a guardian angel
in the book of Tobit, for instance.
You know, there's a lot of that stuff in the history of the church.
What do you think, Father?
Is there a linkage between all these concepts?
i i think i think st rafael is a good example because
Yeah, I think I think we get hung up on the guarding element.
And it's really more that concept.
When you go to its roots in second-table Judaism and early Christianity is much closer to a guiding angel.
Right. And you can see how state Rafael kind of guides the companies and guides
to open on his journey. I mean, there are instances where he guards him from something or helps him guard himself.
But overall it's...
It's one of this guiding idea.
And guiding and shaping.
Now, when you contrast it with what we were talking about in the first half, right?
So a demonic spirit is going to try to guide people to destruction, right?
Whereas an angelic being is going to try to guide someone back toward God, guide them
to Christ, guide them back to God.
so
So part of the purpose of like the prayer to the guardian angel is to try to help to
our selves to that guidance, right, to make us more sensitive to it.
And you know, and again, this isn't instead of the guidance of the Holy Spirit, right?
Or instead of...
anything right it's very much both and right but I think I think that guiding element is actually the
the most pertinent element more even more than guarding person. So it's a little bit of a misleading
name and perhaps this is guiding angel okay yeah perfect yeah thank you that was kind of
the source of my questioning.
Cause I know there's also like in my morning prayers,
at least when I in the prayers in my guardian angel
and mentions something along the lines of like
protect me against like the demons
and help make sure that they don't subdue my mortal body
and like almost seeing like it's talking about possession
in the sense that you're talking about in the first half.
Yeah.
I'm sure you guys.
talk more about it.
And that's kind of all of a piece too, right?
Like, a guardian angel can't go against your will, won't generally go against your will.
Like, I'm going to send, you know, what can he do, right?
So like, you know, and I'm going to send means I'm going to cooperate with demons.
That's what that means.
So the guiding function and the guarding function in a lot of ways are kind of the same
thing.
Yeah, and we don't want to over-literalize the metaphor, right?
There's like sort of the Frank Pretty version that the attacks of the demons
is like they're swinging in invisible flaming sword at you and like your
guardian angel parries it with his sword or something, right?
This is going on and you can't see it.
The way that demons attack us is by tempting us to sin.
Right.
By putting evil thoughts in our minds, right?
Those are the attacks we're talking about.
Yeah.
And so we're asking the
to help protect us and strengthen us against those attacks so that we don't fall for them.
Right? Yeah. And it ended up getting captured by and enslaved by sin.
Yep. Yep. All right. Thank you very much, Nicholas. Thank you.
God be with you on your pilgrimage. All right. We're going to go ahead and roll on.
I know we have some other callers that are waiting. God willing, we'll get to a couple at least in the third half.
but uh
All right, demons and second temple Judaism.
That's a significant contrast.
Yeah, it's right.
Get excited everybody.
We're going to talk about giants.
And I mean, there's some interesting similarities, although not exactly the same,
but there's definitely some interesting similarities to the pagan concepts that we've been discussing.
Right.
So origins of demons and second temple Judaism, we talked about the Greek view, the Roman view.
And when we talk about demons, we're not talking about all evil spirits, right?
So we're not talking about like the gods of the nations, right?
Right.
In the sense that we've talked about them like with the Tower of Babel, right?
What we're talking about are the bodyless, unclean spirits that come and possess people,
that torment people, right?
They're especially prominent in the synoptic gospels.
And I say the synoptic gospels because there are no exorcisms in St. John's Gospel.
You
but in St. Matthew, St. Mark, and St. Luke's Gospels, there are lots of exorcisms.
And you find these kind of spirits in the same sense that you find in the synoptic
Gospels, for example, in Tobit that we just mentioned with the collar. So the second temple period,
very clearly there, but you don't find that particular kind of phenomena.
and described that much, well not really at all in the Torah for example.
And the places where you start seeing references to like unclean spirits are for example in
first through fourth kingdoms, first and second Samuel, first and second kings, but that's one
continuous story that ends in the exile, so this is a text that's written relatively.
the exile, right? Yeah, like like Saul, for instance, when the Holy Spirit departs from him, he then gets a
attacked by this demon.
Uncleaned spirit.
Yeah.
And so you see that show yet.
But again, this is in the exilic period.
So this is a phenomenon that primarily gets described
in the context of second-table Judaism in terms
of texts that we have.
Right.
I am certain there was an understanding.
So if you're asking, right, well, if we say that,
that's true, and that happened to Saul,
while Saul is around 1000 BC, right?
The ancient Israelite religion had some understanding of this and where they came from and I'll say I agree with you the problem is it's hard to know.
Yeah, because we don't have any extra biblical texts from 1000 BC Jewish extra biblical text or Israelite extra biblical text.
Right.
Unless you count like two and three line inscriptions.
And even then, a lot of those are biblical names.
or related to biblical events, right?
So they're only barely extrabiblical
and they're tiny inscriptions and things, right?
We're not talking about a text,
talking about the origin of demons.
But we do have those kind of texts
once we get to the Second Temple period.
So we at least know at that point
what was being thought
as we move toward the New Testament.
And then we can sort of trace that out
from the Second Temple period
into the new testament, into the
early church and the fathers, right? So that's where we're going here in this second half.
Now of course, we've talked a bunch on the show, it's so we're not going to belabor it again,
about the way this is presented in the book of Enic in Jubilee's. And yes, I say Enic,
I know he's a sleigh stack. I don't care. It's hard for me.
If it bothers you too bad.
But the book of the Anakin Jubilee is right. We've talked about that right that these are the spirits of the Nephilim who are killed in the flood. Right. Now remember the Nephilim are semi divine. The Nephilim are.
The heroes of old the men of her noun, right. These are so what we find here as we've talked about before is not a rejection of the pagan stories. Yeah. Right.
It's a different interpretation of what's really going on.
They agree with the pagans on the facts.
right that there were these heroes that they were in some sense semi-divine that there were these
Des Moines involved in their conception and their existence and their lives just you know how that's
morally understood is very different in fact opposite right right just like again pagans having
their guardian demons you know thumbs up it's a good thing yeah Christians looking at pagans with
with guardian demons, thumbs down.
So, and we've talked about the story about mastima in Jubilee's where mastima is one of the leaders of those now disembodied at Nephilim who they're going to get thrown into the abyss along with their fallen angel parents and
uh...
Master Migos and begs on their behalf to God to allow them to
stay sort of at large wandering around roaming the world. Again, you see the parallels.
But they promise that they'll just afflict wicked people.
And God, of course, allows their request. He lets 10% of them stick around on Earth
because God's plan is to use them afflicting the wicked to bring the wicked to repentance.
God wants to use them to help bring those people to the world.
to salvation and bring good out of their evil, sort of against their desires.
And this plays out in various levels of detail in different parts of the Dead Sea Scrolls.
Dead Sea Scrolls, of course, are from an inocent community at Comoron.
So you have all kinds of taxonomy about Boliol and the demonic spirits, and it's all very
consistent with that kind of idea.
But...
one important thing to emphasize here in the Second Temple period is it's not just in
not cake of Judaism that has this view.
Right.
And this is important as we're going to now move into the New Testament and move into
the early church fathers because Christianity is not just a Second Temple Judaism.
It is specifically a form of second temple fair.
as we've said. So we have a nice quote from Josephus, a Pharisee in his antiquities about where he
believes these unclean spirits come from. Yeah. Okay. So this is Josephus and antiquities 3, 1.
He writes this. Now this posterity of Seth continued to esteem God as the Lord of the universe
and to have...
an entire regard to virtue for seven generations. But in process of time they were perverted,
and forsook the practices of their forefathers, and did neither pay those honors to God which
were appointed them nor had they any concern to do justice towards men. But for what degree of zeal
they had formally shown for virtue they now showed by their actions a double degree of wickedness,
whereby they made God to be their enemy. For many angels of God accompanied with women
and begat sons that proved unjust.
and despisers of all that was good, on account of the confidence they had in their own strength.
For the tradition is that these men did what resembled the acts of those whom the Greeks called giants.
But Noah was very uneasy at what they did, and being displeased of their conduct persuaded them to
change their dispositions and their acts for the better, but seeing they did not yield to him,
but were slaves to their wicked pleasures, he was afraid they would kill him together with his wife
and children, and those they had married, so he departed out of that land.
So it's
It's interesting. I mean, he basically says that there's this some kind of union between
angels and humans and you get giants and connects it to the Greek giants.
Yeah. Yeah.
Right. Can next it to the Greek story, right, regarding the giants, which so we'll get to that in a
second. Also, I want to note, I bet that long quotes were some of you because when he started out,
now he's talking about the descendants.
of Seth. And I bet you thought for a second that he was going to take the rabbinic Jewish
tack and say it's it's uh, sons of Seth and and daughters of Kane. But he served you
all and went straight for uh, Nephilim. Um, but uh, yeah. So the place where the giants
those who don't just know this off the top of their head.
The terms of...
We believe is this is part of, so the Titans were the children of Gaia, right?
The earth.
They're kind of like the initial group of gods that are ruling over everything.
And the Titans, right, then get overthrown by the Olympians.
Zeus at all.
Zeus and his brothers, right, the Hades and Poseidon, and their various...
relations. They overthrow the Titans and imprison them in Tartarus. Right. And if you played
the God of War games, you've killed all these people. But anyway, so so Gaia became very angry.
right? The earth became very angry that the Olympians had sort of...
often imprisoned her children. And so brought forth these monsters. We talked about Typhon in one episode.
I think it was in the Antichrist episode. We talked about Typhon.
But also the Giants. At the word Giante in Greek literally means the sons of Gaea.
Yeah. Those born of Gaea. The earth born. But it's not earth born in the sense of dirt, right?
That's a materialist reading. Right. Right. They met gay at like the goddess who is the earth.
the spirit of the earth, the world's soul. Right. Right. And they then came to take revenge,
basically. Right. And engaged in all this horrific evil behavior. Right.
Recky, the world was then led to the Gigantomaki where they had to be defeated and driven out. Right.
And so that's that's the comparison that Josephus is making there. Yeah. And we should say Josephus
This is a first...
century Jew. Yes, an aferacy. An aferacy, yeah. In particular. And so what we find is this isn't a unique
connection that Josephus makes between the Titans and the angels who rebelled in the time of Noah
and then the Olympians and the Nephilim.
In fact, this becomes, this connection becomes part and parcel of early Christianity.
Yeah.
So early Christians, again, are basically agreeing with pagans on the basic shape of the story
and the players involved, but giving a very different analysis of all of it.
Right.
Right. Because in their minds, the Greeks have preserved some correct information,
but it's been distorted by the demons they're worshipping.
Yeah. Right in the same way that we talked about, you know, the bail cycle is Prodevil propaganda,
right? Really on. Yeah. I mean, like, like, you know, exhibit A, right, is in second Peter,
chapter two, where he talks about the angels who fell from the former state being bound up in
literally in Tartarus as the actual word that he uses. I mean, he just uses the straight word for the
the deepest part of Greek hell. Yes, the place of the where the Titans are in prison. So, yeah,
Yeah.
That's the only place where the word tartarists appears in the Greek Bible, old or new testaments.
But yeah, so let's clearly make it that connection.
There's plenty of other places we could talk about too, like the high-altred disease at
Pergamon and Revelation being referred to as the throne of Satan, right?
Like, these are connections that are just day regure.
this continues then past this connection between the watchers
the Titans and the Olympians of the demons, continues in the Church of others, especially
the earliest Church of others.
So for example, in the eighth of the Clementine homilies in section 15, I guess most people
say it's the third century, maybe second century.
So whoever, yeah, yeah, with discussion about who wrote it exactly.
But in any event it says this.
But from their unhallowed intercourse,
intercourse,
Spurious men sprang.
That's great.
I love the alliteration there.
Good translation.
Much greater in stature than ordinary men,
whom they afterwards called giants.
Not those dragon-footed giants who waged war against God
as those blasphemous myths of the Greeks do sing,
but wild in manners,
and greater than men in size,
and as much as they were sprung of angels,
yet less than angels,
as they were...
of women. Yeah. And what place for that translation is bad is that who wage war against God should be who
wage war against Zeus. Against Zeus. Yeah. Yeah. That's the thing is like, like, is they, they have, you
know, zeo gets used to mean just God and a lot of well, a lot of translators translated as just God.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. That's what they're referring to. Right. They were against the divine. Right.
against the gods in the blasphemous this of the Greeks, right?
Yeah, I noticed the the myths that the Greeks sing.
So we're still old school here. We're still
singing the poetry. Yeah.
Yeah, and then as late as
St. Ambrose,
it is homily on Noah and the art.
Number four section eight.
Yeah, so what he has to say is the
the Nephilim were on earth in those days, so he's quoting from Genesis 6.
Then he goes, honestly, the author of the divine scripture does not mean that those giants must be considered, according to the tradition of poets.
Of course he means the Greek pagan poets, as sons of the earth, but asserts that those whom he defines with such a name because of the extraordinary size of their body were generated by angels and women.
So, um...
Yeah, so again, right, he's directly connecting this to the story is this is he's reading Genesis
here as correcting the pagan Greek and Roman stories.
Yeah, and so he's fourth century.
He dies in the right at the very end of the fourth century.
Yeah.
And then so that's on the sort of Titans and Watchers being equated side.
We also have a lot of great stuff on the connection between the Olympus.
the Indians and the demons.
Yeah, so St. Justin Martyr, also known as Justin the philosopher, in his second apology,
chapter five, he writes this, but the angels transgressed this appointment.
So he's mid-second century, ever went, by the way.
The angels transgressed this appointment and were captivated by love of women and begat
children who are those that are called demons.
And besides, they afterwards subdued the human race to themselves, partly by magical
writings and partly by fears in the punishments they occasioned and P-
Partly by teaching them to offer sacrifices and incense and libations, of which things they
stood in need after they were enslaved by lustful passions, and among men they sowed murders,
wars, adulteries, and tempered deeds in all wickedness.
Once also the poets and mythologists, not knowing that it was the angels and those demons
who had been begotten by them that did these things to men and women, and cities and nations
which they related, ascribed them to Zeus himself, and to those who were counted to be his
very offspring.
the offspring of those who were called his brothers, Poseidon.
and Hades, and to the children again of these offspring. For whatever name each of the angels
had given to himself and his children, by that name they called them. So this is St. Justin
like correcting the Greeks, correcting, you know, Greek mythology and saying, no, no,
no, it wasn't Zeus and Poseidon and Hades. This was the watchers coming down and well
in the world. For him the dead Nephilim become demons. Yeah. Right. He's either those
demons and those demons caused themselves to be worshipped and corrupt.
humanity and give themselves names like Zeus, Poseidon, Hades, and all the other Greek
gods.
The Olympian gods are being connected with the demons of Greek lore and demons of Christian
and Jewish lore.
I should say.
Right.
The children of the fallen angels.
Yeah.
So another early
Christian source Athenagoras in his text called the plea for the Christians, chapter 25. He writes,
these angels then, who have fallen from heaven, and haunt the air in the earth, and are no longer
able to rise to heavenly things, and the souls of the giants, which are the demons who wander about
the world, perform actions similar, the one that is the demons, to the natures they have received,
the other, other that is the angels, to the appetites they have indulged.
Right, now...
But an important thing here is that nature they have received versus the appetites they
have indulged.
Right.
So the angels here are fallen from their former estate, whereas the demons, the dead
giants have become demons because they become corrupted more on that in a minute.
Right.
They're humans, they're dead humans.
Yeah.
What it is.
Okay.
And Gouraus by the way is also second century, so very, very early on.
Then you got Komodianus in his instructions, chapter 3,
when Almighty God to beautify the nature of the world will, that the sun, that, excuse me,
will that the earth should be visited by angels.
When they were sent down, they despised His laws, such was the beauty of women that it turned them aside
so that being contaminated, they could not return to heaven.
Rebels from God, they uttered words against Him.
Then the highest uttered His judgment against them.
and from their seed
giants are said to have been born. By them, arts were made known in the earth, and they
taught the dying of wool and everything which is done, and to them, when they died, men
erected images. But the Almighty, because they were of an evil seed, did not approve
that when dead, they should be brought back from death, whence wandering, they now subvert
many bodies. And it is such as these, especially that ye this day worship and pray to as gods.
being the Roman Pagats.
in this. Yeah. So there's this, you know, not only is he saying that it's these are the
dead giants, but he also seems to suggest that they're not going to be resurrected from
the dead. But that they wander the earth. And, and that these are the gods that the
pagans are praying to. Yes, they're praying to dead humans sacrifice to the dead humans
Effectively yes, then giants yes, yeah, yeah
Another little piece of this
A little piece of this picture.
We get from Kelsus by way of origin.
So we haven't brought him up in a while on the show.
Probably not since the Queen stood at that right hand, but maybe at some point I did.
Yeah, Kelsus is this early pagan critic against Christianity.
And origin in the second century sort of the great, the best attack anybody came up with
on Christian.
Christianity. Yeah, right. And it wasn't just sort of a one pronged attack. It was every argument from a pagan Roman perspective that you could level against Christianity, right?
So in the Queen's Earth, I right now we talked about it from the perspective of he he attacked the idea that Mary, because she was a peasant, since the Theotokos was a peasant. How could she be the mother of a king?
Yeah, or a lot.
Yeah, but he knew he knew her name and everything.
in the second century, this Roman pagan, which as we said then, implies that Christians were talking about
her in the second century, such that would be an attack. But one of his arguments, one of his
arguments against Christianity is, look, Christians are telling people not to worship, not to make offerings
to the day monies, not to worship the gods.
And that keeps happening.
The gods...
and especially the demonets are gonna get angry.
Yeah, we know what happens in the world.
They're gonna attack us.
They're gonna kill us all and wipe out our cities
and plunge everything into chaos and destruction.
So it's the argument from demons.
They were a mechanism.
We've gotta keep them happy, right?
And origin's response is into origin writes contra-celsus,
right, against Celsius, responding to all of these arguments.
and his
response to this is, well, Christians don't have to worry about demons about
day monies because, you know, we've got the Holy Spirit and look at all the
exorcisms going on. Right? We have authority over them. So we're not worried
about it. It's you who are going to be in trouble if the demon get mad. Yeah.
Not the Christians. So you just can you problem? Yeah. Yeah. If you just
convert, you wouldn't have this problem. Yes. Just become a Christian and you
you would have to worry about it.
Yeah, and another interesting note here is that within this, and if you understand what
we're saying in the first half about Genii, origins has not only our sort of Christians
immune to the working of demons that don't have to fear them, but he even argues Christians
are immune to fate, which is an interesting statement in terms of his understanding.
at least is a-
expressed here. It's hard to make it make sense with on first principles, because origin seems
like he has to be a pretty hard determinist. All things considered, right? At least the way he's
been presented, but here he argues that, yeah, that kind of pagan fatalism is true for pagans,
because they're sort of enslaved to these demonic spirits who control their fate and their destiny.
right? But Christians are in
You too, fate and destiny.
Christians are free because they're free of those spirits,
right?
Which also says something about his view of God.
Yeah.
Which I'd say sorry Calvinists,
but disagreeing with origin,
fair enough, right?
Um,
that's, so I can't really throw that one at you this time.
Calvinist friends.
Um, but
But it is interesting.
It is an interesting note there.
Like I said, it's hard to jive with things he says elsewhere, at least as they're commonly
interpreted.
Yeah.
Well, he's not a saint.
So we don't have to make it all work.
And even if it were, yeah.
Just interesting.
Yeah.
Everybody needs to write a dissertation.
There you go.
You're welcome.
Yeah.
I mean, and we should say like that thing that Komodiana says about no resurrection.
again like this is not
We're not saying that everything these guys say is dogman.
You have to this is not the love the needs and the Persians.
It's not the picture.
Yeah.
But it shows us an understanding.
Right.
The connections that we're being made.
Yeah.
So yeah.
Well, you know, a quote that we've mentioned in the past, but it's been, I think it's been
a while, but I think it's good to bring up again from a really obscure church father
that no one's ever heard of named St. John Chrysostom.
Yeah, who I don't know who this guy yeah, this isn't his four discourses on the rich man and Lazarus so these are these are homilies, you know, discourses, they're homilies.
He says this.
He says here before I go on, I want to remove a wrong impression from your minds.
So he's going to do a little debunking for it is a fact that many of the less instructed think that the souls of those who die of violent death become wandering spirits.
Okay.
This is not so. I repeat, it is not so. It isn't the souls of those who die of violet
death that become demons, but rather the souls of those who live in sin. Not that their
nature is changed, but that in their desires they imitate the evil nature of demons.
Showing this very thing to the Jews, Christ said, you are of your father the devil. He said
that they were the children of the devil not because they were changed into a nature like
the kids.
Bye.
because they did the kinds of things he did.
For the same reason he adds,
and your will is to do your father's desires.
Also, John says, you brutive vipers
who warned you to flee from the wrath to come,
bear fruit that befits your penance
and do not presume to say to yourselves,
we have Abraham as our father.
The scripture therefore usually bases the laws
of relationship not on natural origin,
but on good or evil disposition.
And if anyone acts like or does the same things
there's a certain group, this one.
Scripture declares him to be their son or their brother.
Yes.
So, yeah, lots going on.
It's a more full form of the quote.
This is a longer quote than we've read typically in the past,
because we want to make a couple points here in this context.
So we have the part that we've read before, right,
which is you don't become a demon in a wandering spirit, right?
He equates those two ideas.
You don't become that because you died of violent death.
And that's something people still believe today, right?
Like you have a ghost in a house
because someone was murdered there, right?
Yeah.
Right.
But no, the person who becomes a demon,
who becomes a wandering spirit, it's because of their evil,
right?
Yeah, because they lived like a demon before death.
That way, and have become like them.
But notice, so, and this is the reason
the longer form.
We're going to make this point about, I mean, spoilers.
We're going to make this point about, say, to Guston in the third half, too.
So, right, we've dealt with it.
We dealt with this in the, the, the, the, the, the, the giants episode, which will live in
infamy.
But the fact that there's this transition in the fifth century in terms of the
fathers holding to, like the quotes we've been reading, holding to this kind of
Second temple Jewish and then early Christian
consensus about not just the origin of demons, but who the Nephilim were some
version of the watcher story, etc., to adopting the rabbinic Jewish view regarding the sons of Seth and
the daughters of Kane. Right? And we talked about the reasons for that transition that sort of paganism,
the kind of pagan ritual life that explained what that was referring to had gone away, so they didn't
see it. We talked about how
like St. John Cache and St. John Chrysostom
in his second set of homilies on Genesis.
It's not clear what his view is in the first set.
In the second set of homilies on Genesis,
he makes arguments about why he holds the Sethite view
and not the other view.
But he talked about how important it is
and St. Augustine makes arguments.
How important it is that they make arguments, right?
Because none of those church fathers normally make arguments.
They just...
each. Yeah, they just say this is what this is referring to. But those fathers are aware
that the previous fathers taught something different. Yes, they have to engage with that.
And so they feel the need to and they model for us. Yes, if you're saying something that
disagrees with the fathers, you need to have a pretty good argument, right? So they're
interacting with that and they're making arguments, right? But even though they ultimately reject...
the view that we've put forward pretty consistently on this show, that what's being talked about is not literally an angel and a human having a baby that has like half human and half angel DNA or something.
Because, just to re-underline this thing here, DNA is a material phenomenon.
right angels.
No one knew about right.
Right.
But how are you conceive of it?
Like angels are not material.
I mean, but I replay answered mules or ligers, whatever.
Like anyone who comment, any of the fathers, I think this is true.
Any of the fathers who comment on whether angels can reproduce,
say that they can't, that they don't have the ability to reproduce.
Yeah, we'll talk more about that.
But that's like we're that a third half and the third half.
We get that demon sex everybody.
Yeah, that's right.
Exactly, but but like for instance St. John Damascus
says that they're not male and female because they don't, you know, there's no root for
that.
It happened to their own kind.
Yeah.
So, but right.
So, they're not making that literal claim.
Right.
Those previous fathers are not making that literal claim.
That's not what the second double Jewish view was.
But that they were understanding that within a ritual context that involved possession,
that involved sexual rituals at the conception of the king.
kings and temple prostitutes, right? That's what was going on, right? If you had the GoPro
and the Tartus. And the prasostum here is making this linkage between fathers and sons
and saying that's where I'm going. Yeah. Go jump the gun. Right. So, um, what St. Augustine
and St. John Cashin and St. John Chris.
system, reject is that literal view. What they argue against is that literal view, which
we're saying is not what the earlier fathers were actually trying to say. Yeah. But that
the later fathers, because paganism was gone, those kind of rituals weren't taking place,
they didn't understand that context, right? To me, what we're seeing now and what we're
talking about tonight is honestly the real linchpin of our argument that to me proves it
be on the shadow of it.
doubt in this regard because what we're starting to see here what we're seeing
here with St. John Chrysostom and what we're going to see with St. Augustine is
that they have all the pieces of our view.
Right. What we say in our view, our view meaning like me, Father Andrew, Lord of
Spirit show, right, what we've put forward in terms of what was really going on.
All the pieces of that are present in these fathers who quote unquote rejects.
that view. Yeah, I think what Chris saw just they just have it connected them. Yeah, they haven't
been connected what the earlier father said to these pieces that they believe at a firm. Yeah, I
think what Chris Austin is doing here is really a refinement really a refinement of what some of
the earlier fathers were saying, even though he's putting it in terms of I don't I don't agree with
that. Right. He's not making that connection. But what he says here is what does it mean?
For one of these dead people who's become a demon to have a fallen angel is their father.
Right.
He's saying it means they imitate them and do what they do.
Yeah, they're evil.
Right?
Not that they're biologically descended.
That's the argument St. John Chrysostom is making.
So St. John Chrysostom's argument here could be used to counter the argument he makes
in his second set of homilies on Genesis.
Genesis 6.
Right. And I think that if again, we took the Tartus to see St. John Christophe, right?
And polished up our Greek a lot. Someone could put that out to him, right? And be like,
no, when St. Aaron, NAS, right, not I'm right in your wrongs at John Christophe, but when
St. Aaron, NAS, when St. Justin Martyr, when they say these things, they're talking about
what you're talking about.